<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A light vnto the vnlearned: or, The principles of the doctrine of Christ Set downe most briefely, for the use of yong and ignorant persons. To be learned and remembred, at all times: but specially, when they would come to the holy communion. Divided into eight sections.</title>
            <author>Inman, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854602</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854602</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20029</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20029)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1312:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A light vnto the vnlearned: or, The principles of the doctrine of Christ Set downe most briefely, for the use of yong and ignorant persons. To be learned and remembred, at all times: but specially, when they would come to the holy communion. Divided into eight sections.</title>
                  <author>Inman, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat for George Lathum, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Brasen Serpent,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: Fran: Inman.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Person and offices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20029:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20029:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LIGHT VNTO THE VNLEARNED: OR, THE PRINCIPLES OF THE DOCTRINE OF CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Set downe moſt briefely, for the uſe of yong and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Perſons. To be learned and remembred, at all times: but ſpecially, when they would come to the holy Communion.</p>
            <p>Divided into eight Sections.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt</hi> for <hi>George Lathum,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the Signe of the Braſen Serpent. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20029:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20029:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Propound (Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) in this moſt briefe Treatiſe, the principall Grounds of our Religion, in the moſt compendious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The cauſe of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie is this: There be many poore ſervants and laborers; many that are of trades and manuall Sciences; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aged Perſons of weake and decaied memories: Of theſe, ſome never learned ſo much as to reade, ſome very little, and the moſt of them haue, or will have, ſmall leiſure to learne long diſcourſes: the world, or other vanities, taking up their thoughts and cares. Yet all theſe haue immortall ſoules, to remaine after a few daies, in eternall ioyes, or in endleſſe paines. Of theſe care muſt be had: and the rather, becauſe many of them haue little care of themſelues. To theſe, the longeſt tractates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpleaſing, I direct the ſhorteſt. For, better a little well learned, then a great deale not learned at all. In which, I comprehend much matter in few words: and draw together, into the narroweſt
<pb facs="tcp:20029:3"/>ſpace, thoſe things, which I iudged moſt needfull for them to know unto ſalvation. I haue confirmed the ſame in the margent with proofes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſelected out of many which might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: and for their greater eaſe and benefit, I haue expreſſed the words themſelues; and where neede is, as the ſtreightneſſe of roome would permit, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed them: that they may ſee herein, not man teaching them, but God. Jf they would take a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paines, to learne theſe few points without booke, they might haue matter of good meditation, when they are about their workes, and travailing in worldly affaires: and ſo their earthly dealings ſhould be more bleſſed. Alſo, they may receiue greater profite by the Scriptures they reade, and Sermons they heare, when they know to what head or ground of Doctrine, to referre that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. And may by this meanes come better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Lords Table. Wherefore, I earneſtly exhort them, as from my heart deſiring their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to reteine the grounds of heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in perfect memorie: to labour to haue their hearts affected therewith: and to manifeſt there knowledge by an holy converſation. That living vertuouſly, they may die comfortably: and after this ſhort and uncertaine life is ended, come to bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed immortalitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fran: Inman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20029:3"/>
            <head>THE PRINCIPLES of the DOCTRINE of CHRIST, ſet downe moſt briefely.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD is a<note n="1" place="margin">Ioh. 4.24. God is a Spirit.</note> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual<note n="*" place="margin">This word, <hi>eſſence,</hi> ſignifieth a being. God is the firſt and chiefeſt being. He ſaith. <hi>Exod. 3.14. I am:</hi> implying his ſelfe-being. And he giueth beeing to all other things.</note> Eſſence,<note n="2" place="margin">Pſal. 90. verſe 2. From everlaſting to everlaſting thou art God. Ier. 23.24. I fill heauen and earth.</note> infinite and<note n="3" place="margin">Gen. 17.1. I am the Almightie God.</note> Almightie,<note n="4" place="margin">Pſal. 147.5. His underſtanding is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</note> moſt Wiſe and<note n="5" place="margin">Iſa. 6.3. Holy, holy, holy is the Lord of hoſts.</note> moſt Holy,<note n="6" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3. The Father of mercies.</note> moſt Mercifull and<note n="7" place="margin">Pſal. 11.7. The juſt Lord loveth juſtice.</note> moſt Iuſt.</p>
               <p>The Godhead is diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20029:4"/>into<note n="1" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.7. There are three that beare record in heauen, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt: and theſe three are one.</note> three divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: the Father, who is of himſelfe; the Sonne, who is of the Father; the holy Ghoſt, who is of them both.</p>
               <p>All theſe three are one, and the ſame God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 2.</head>
               <p>This God; the Father, the Son, the holy Ghoſt;<note n="2" place="margin">Nehem. 9.6. Thou haſt made heauen, the heauen of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens with all their hoſte, the earth and all things that are therein, the ſeas and all that is therein; and thou preſerveſt them all.</note> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things: things inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as Angels; and viſible, as Men, and other creatures. And he gouerneth them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 3.</head>
               <p>God created our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen. 1.27. God created man in his owne image.</hi> Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled his Creator in excellent gifts: in ſoule, in body, in both.</note> bleſſed eſtate. <hi>Hee adorned their ſoules with wiſe-dome, and righteouſneſſe: their bodies with beautie, and glorie: and both with immortalitie, and dominion over other creatures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by the<note n="4" place="margin">Gen. 3.4, 5. The ſerpent ſaid unto the woman yee ſhall not ſurely die: — Yee ſhall be as Gods—</note> inticement of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20029:4"/>the Divell, they<note n="1" place="margin">Gen. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. When the woman ſaw, that the tree was — to bee deſired to make one wiſe, <hi>(to wit, in her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced iudgement)</hi> ſhee tooke of the fruite thereof, and did eate: and gaue alſo unto her husband —</note> fell willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from God, and<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom. 5.19. By the diſobedience of one man, many were made ſinners.</hi> This man was <hi>Adam,</hi> our firſt parent: his foſleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who are many, which iſſue by genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from him, are made ſinners by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of his ſinne.</note> wee, their poſterity, fel with them. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, our whole nature is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and inclined to all evil. Whereupon wee are<note n="3" place="margin">Deut. 27.26. <hi>and</hi> Gal. 3.10. Curſed is every one that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not in al things which are written in the booke of the law, to doe them.
<p>
                        <hi>The curſe of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth all troubles of this life; and torment of the text.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> ſubject to eternall miſerie: beginning in this life, in manifold calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and continuing after this life, in unquenchable fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="4" place="margin">Gal 4.4, 5. God ſent forth his Sonne — made under the law: to redeeme them that were under the law.</note>To redeeme us out of this miſerie, and to bring us againe to felicitie, God hath given to us a Sauiour: His Sonne, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Chriſt conſiſteth of<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh. 1.14. The word was made fleſh.</hi> That is, the Sonne of God was made man: and ſo is, both the Sonne of God; and the Sonne of man.</note> two natures: a divine nature, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is perfect God: and an humane nature, whereby he is perfect man.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20029:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That being God, he might be able to beare the puniſhment due to us: and might make the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his manhood of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite value. And being man, ſinne might be puniſhed in that nature which ſinned: and in the ſame, the righteouſneſſe of the law might be fulfilled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He hath three offices: Hee is a<note n="1" place="margin">Heb. 5.5. God glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Chriſt, to bee made an high Prieſt.</note> Prieſt. a<note n="2" place="margin">Luk. 7.16. A great Prophet is riſen up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us.</note> Prophet, and a<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk. 1.33. He ſhall reigne for ever, over the houſe of Iacob.</hi> That is, over the whole Church of God: which was firſt confined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Iacobs</hi> familie: and now into it all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are adopted.</note> King.</p>
               <p>He is a Prieſt, to make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction &amp; interceſsion for us.</p>
               <p>Hee maketh ſatisfaction, by<note n="4" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24. His owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes, in his owne body, on the tree.</note> ſuffering the puniſhment of our ſinnes: and by<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom. 5.19. By the obedience of one, ſhall many be made righteous.</hi> This one is Christ: the whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of beleevers in him, are made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by imputation of his righteouſneſſe.</note> fulfilling, on our behalfe, all the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the law.</p>
               <p>He maketh interceſsion, by<note n="6" place="margin">Heb. 9.24. Chriſt is entred into heauen, to appeare in the preſence of God for us, <hi>His appearing hath the force of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating.</hi>
                  </note> intreating God the Father to accept his ſatisfaction for us.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20029:5"/>
               <p>He is a Prophet,<note n="1" place="margin">Ioh. 15.15. All things that I haue heard of my Father, I haue made knowne unto you.</note> to teach us the will of God; and the meanes of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>He is a King, to governe us: and to<note n="2" place="margin">Ioh. 10.28. My ſheepe ſhal never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: none ſhall pluck the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of my hand.</note> keepe us in the way of ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 5.</head>
               <p>Of this Saviour, and of his ſalvation, we are<note n="3" place="margin">Ioh. 3.36. He that beleeueth on the Sonne, hath everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</note> partakers by faith in him.</p>
               <p>Faith is a ſpeciall grace of God, whereby wee<note n="4" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12. To as many as received him, he gave power to become the ſons of God: even to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleeue on his name. <hi>Here, the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Chriſt, is the ſame with beleeving on Chriſt. Therefore when hee is beleeved on, he is received.</hi>
                  </note> apply Chriſt to our ſelues: and are<note n="5" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.13. Theſe things haue I write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> unto you, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue on the name of the Son of God, that yee may know, that yee haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</note> aſſured, through his merits, of our eternall ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 6.</head>
               <p>They which beleeue in Chriſt, are<note n="6" place="margin">Act. 13.39. By him all that beleeue, are juſtified.</note> iuſtified, and<note n="7" place="margin">Act. 15.9. By faith our hearts are purified.</note> ſanctified: and therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be<note n="8" place="margin">Ioh. 15.5. He that abideth in me — bringeth foorth much fruite.</note> plentifull in all good workes.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20029:6"/>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 7.</head>
               <p>We muſt be carefull to uſe all good means, that faith may be wrought, and increaſed in us.</p>
               <p>The principall meanes are three: the hearing of the word of God, the receiving of the Sacraments, and Prayer.</p>
               <p>Wee muſt heare the word of God with<note n="1" place="margin">Act. 15.14. The Lord opened the heart of Lydia, that ſhee attended unto the things which were ſpoken.</note> diligent attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and keepe it in our hearts by<note n="2" place="margin">Pſa. 1.1, 2. Bleſſed is the man that — doth meditate in the law of the Lord, day and night.</note> continuall meditation.</p>
               <p>The Sacraments are holy<note n="3" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom. 4.11. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham received the ſigne of circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith.</hi> As circumciſion was a ſigne of the Covenant of Grace, and a ſeale to aſſure the beleevers the remiſſion of ſinnes: ſo are the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> ſignes and ſeales, by which God declareth and ſealeth, for the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes, and life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, to every beleever.</p>
               <p>There be two Sacraments Baptiſme, and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
               <p>Baptiſme is a Sacrament,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20029:6"/>whereby is ſealed to us, our<note n="1" place="margin">Circumciſion ſealed to the people of Iſrael, that God for the merit of the promiſed ſeede would bee their God: and Baptiſme, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that Sacrament, ſealeth the ſame to us.</note> receiving into the Covenant of Grace, our<note n="2" place="margin">Gal. 3.27. As ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as haue beene baptized into Chriſt, haue put on Chriſt.</note> ingrafting into Chriſt, and our<note n="3" place="margin">Tit. 3.5. God ſaved us, by the waſhing of regeneration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the holy Ghoſt.</note> regeneration by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>The Lords Supper is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, whereby is ſealed to us, the continuance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of the benefits con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Baptiſme. <hi>Namely our remaining in the Covenant of Grace: our further ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into Chriſt, and regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his Spirit: and ſo our nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer union and communion with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Foure things are required to the receiving of the Lords Supper. Knowledge of the Grounds of Religion:<note n="4" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod. 12. The poſts of every mans houſe were ſprinkled with the blood of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall Lambe:</hi> So eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man muſt haue the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, by faith imputed to himſelfe. This faith muſt ſhew it ſelfe in the fruits thereof.</note> Faith in Chriſt: Repentance for our ſinnes: Charitie to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
               <p>Prayer is an<note n="5" place="margin">Pſal. 143.6. My ſoule thirſteth after thee, as a thirſty land.</note> earneſt deſire of a<note n="6" place="margin">Prov. 28.9. He that turneth away his eare from hearing the law, euen his prayer is abomination.</note> converted heart to God,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20029:7"/>according to his<note n="1" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.14. If wee aske any thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, he heareth us.</note> will, in the<note n="2" place="margin">Ioh. 16.26. Ye ſhall aske in my name.</note> name of Chriſt, with<note n="3" place="margin">Mark. 11.24. What things ſoever ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire when ye pray, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that ye receiue them.</note> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be heard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 8.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Having declared the eſtate of man in this life; what it was in his innocencie, and what it hath beene ſince his fall, both by nature, and by grace: I will alſo ſhew his estate after this life.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE eſtate of the dead is this. The ſoules of the godly are in heauen, in<note n="4" place="margin">Rev. 14 13. Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord — that they may reſt from there labours.</note> bleſſed reſt:<note n="5" place="margin">Rev. 7.9, 10. A great multitude — ſtood before the throne — and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-Salvation to our God — and unto the Lambe.</note> praiſing God; and<note n="6" place="margin">Rev. 6.9, 10. The ſoules of them that were ſhine for the Word of God — cried—How long, Lord—doeſt thou not judge &amp; avenge our blood. —</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring their perfect felicitie.</p>
               <p>The ſoules of the wicked are<note n="7" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.19, 20. The ſpirits, which were diſobedient in the daies of Noah, are in priſon: <hi>So are the ſoules of all that haue died in their ſinnes.</hi>
                  </note> impriſoned in hell: fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the<note n="8" place="margin">Luk. 16.23, 24. The rich man in hell, being in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, cried, I am tormented in this flame.</note> horrour thereof; in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20029:7"/>dreadfull expectation of the ful meaſure of their torments.</p>
               <p>Thus both remaine till the laſt judgement. Then, the dead ſhall<note n="1" place="margin">Ioh. 5.28, 29. All that are in the graues — ſhal come forth.</note> riſe, with their<note n="2" place="margin">Iob 19.26, 27. In my fleſh ſhall I ſee God: — Mine eyes ſhall behold him. —</note> own bodies. The living ſhall be<note n="3" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.51. Wee ſhall not all ſleepe: but wee ſhall all bee changed.</note> changed. And all ſhal<note n="4" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10. Wee muſt all appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the judgement ſeat of Chriſt: that every one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue — according to that hee hath done.—</note> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before Chriſt: and be judged according to their workes.</p>
               <p>After which, the godly ſhall<note n="5" place="margin">Math. 25.34. Come yee bleſſed—inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the kingdome prepared for you — <hi>Then, they ſhall bee Kings.</hi>
                  </note> inherite the kingdome of heauen. They ſhall haue<note n="6" place="margin">Rev. 21.3. God will dwell with men.</note> ful communion with Chriſt: and with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt. There ſoules ſhall be indued with the<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Cor. 13.12. We ſhall ſee face to face.</hi> Evidently and clearely. The morall law, now impoſſible to our fallen nature, ſhall then be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly fulfilled.</note> perfect knowledge, and loue of God. Their bodies ſhall bee<note n="8" place="margin">Phil. 3.21. Chriſt will change our vile body, that it may bee faſhioned like unto his glorious body.</note> like the glorious body of Chriſt. And all ſhall haue<note n="9" place="margin">Pſal 16.11. In thy preſence is fulneſſe of joy.</note> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ioy, for ever.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20029:8"/>
               <p>But the wicked ſhall be caſt<note n="1" place="margin">Luk. 13.27: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me all yee workers of iniquitie.</note> from God: into<note n="2" place="margin">Iude verſ. 13. The blackneſſe of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>The greateſt and thickeſt darkeneſſe.</hi>
                  </note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame darkeneſſe, and<note n="3" place="margin">Dan. 12.2. Shame and everlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> utter confuſion; tormented in ſoule and body, in a<note n="4" place="margin">Rev. 21.8. The fearefull, and unbeleeving, and adhominable — ſhall haue there part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone.</note> lake burning with fire and brimſtone, for<note n="5" place="margin">Math. 25.46. They ſhall goe into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting puniſhment.</note> ever.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:20029:8"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:20029:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
